Guide to the Charles Macauley Research Files circa 1800-1920 MS 3192
New-York Historical Society
Charles Macauley research files
circa 1800-1920
New-York Historical Society
Macauley, Charles, active 1890s-1930s
MS 3192
7.63 Linear feet in 7 record cartons and 2 document boxes
The collection includes Charles Macauley's research files, in the form of unbound scrapbooks in letterboxes, concerning New Jersey's Atlantic Ocean coastline, the state's coastal towns and beaches, shipwrecks off the New Jersey shore, and the presence and work of the U.S. Life-Saving Service (USLSS) in New Jersey from its founding in 1848 to its conclusion in 1915 with the formation of the U.S. Coast Guard. Documents include photographs, including original photos taken by Macauley circa 1890s-1910s; published and hand-drawn maps, including some street maps; picture postcards, perhaps especially of the resort towns; correspondence, including with Sumner Increase Kimball of the USLSS; clippings of articles and published images from newspapers and other print sources; typescript abstracts and extracts of various writings; and Macauley's notes, captions, and compiled lists of lifesaving volunteers, shipwrecks, etc.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Arrangement
The collection retains its original order as compiled by Macauley. The bulk of the documents remain in their original 21 letterboxes. The first 17 of these are organized geographically with documentation related to Sandy Hook in letterbox 1, then advancing southerly along the New Jersey coast to Cape May in letterbox 17. The last 4 letterboxes are thematic with a focus on the history of the U.S. Life Saving Service and on shipwrecks and the laws relating to wrecks. In addition, there are two other boxes of documents: one of correspondence and one of nitrate negatives removed from the scrapbooks.
Biographical / Historical
Little is known of Charles Macauley at this writing. From documents in the collection, it is known that, during the time he compiled these documents, Macauley was a resident of Brooklyn and by about 1908 of Haworth, New Jersey. Some of his correspondence indicates he intended to write a history of the New Jersey shore, though this later sharpened into a focus on the U.S. Life-Saving Service. This resulted in at least one published article: "The Genesis of the U.S. Life Saving Service: Its Birth on Our Coast." New Jersey Historical Society 60 (1937), pp. 116-131.
The U.S. Life-Saving Service (USLSS) began in 1848 as a formal, but volunteer, network administered by the Department of the Treasury to rescue survivors of shipwrecks, initially centered on the New Jersey shore, though later much expanded. The Service became increasingly professionalized in the late 1800s under Superintendent Sumner Increase Kimball. In 1915 the Service merged with the Revenue Cutter Service to become the U.S. Coast Guard.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles Macauley, April 11, 1922. (Some of N-YHS's records have the name misspelled as McCauley.)
Scope and Contents
The collection includes Charles Macauley's research files concerning New Jersey's Atlantic Ocean coastline, the state's coastal towns and beaches, shipwrecks off the New Jersey shore, and the presence and work of the U.S. Life-Saving Service (USLSS) in New Jersey from its founding in 1848 to its conclusion in 1915 with the formation of the U.S. Coast Guard.
The files are in the form of unbound scrapbooks, with the loose sheets held in a series of 21 letterboxes. The first 17 of these boxes proceed geographically, moving from Sandy Hook, which begins the "Jersey Shore" as the state's northernmost point facing the Atlantic Ocean, down to Cape May at the state's southern tip. The final 4 letterboxes are centered on the history (i.e., legislative, administrative, and historical context) of the U.S. Life-Saving Service (USLSS) and on shipwrecks, especially in relation to laws governing wrecks. The container list records Macauley's labels from the letterboxes; [bracketed] labels were added by the processing archivist where the label was missing or obscured, and to identify specific locales documented within a box's range.
For each locale documented in the scrapbooks, there is a rough consistency of subject matter, which covers history and physical description of the place, shipwrecks associated with that locale, and the presence of lifesaving volunteers, stations, and equipment, especially of the USLSS. Documents include photographs, including original photos taken by Macauley; published and hand-drawn maps, including some street maps; picture postcards, perhaps especially of the resort towns; clippings of articles and published images from newspapers and other print sources; typescript abstracts and extracts of various writings; and Macauley's notes, compiled lists (e.g. of the names and dates of lifesaving volunteers at various coastal stations, of shipwrecks associated with a locale). The pages are captioned and most of the original photographs are at least generally identified; these typically are of the lifesaving stations, ships/shipwrecks, and beaches.
Some correspondence can also be found in the scrapbooks. Most of the correspondence, though, is found filed together in alphabetical order by correspondent. The correspondence is primarily research inquiries of libraries, government officials, private sources, other writers on the topics, etc., with the responses often conveying information sought by Macauley. The correspondence is mostly incoming, but there are some drafts of Macauley's outgoing letters. A principal correspondent found in both the correspondence files and in the scrapbooks is Sumner Increase Kimball, the Superintendent of the U.S. Life-Saving Service from 1878 to 1915.
The events represented in the scrapbooks range from the late 1700s to about 1920. Although most of the early-mid 19th century historical references are represented by Macauley's typescript extracts, there are many clippings from original sources. On a skim by the processing archivist, such original documents can be found from as early as about 1800.
Separated Materials
Many of the letterboxes held nitrate negatives of some of the photographs in the boxes. The negatives were removed to a separate box and placed in cold storage. Notations were made within the letterboxes and on the negatives' enclosures to indicate which negatives were removed and from where.
Beaches -- Atlantic Coast (N.J.); Lifesaving stations -- Atlantic Coast (N.J.); Shipwrecks -- Atlantic Coast (N.J.); Cellulose nitrate film.; Letters (correspondence); Maps.; Newspaper clippings.; Photographs.; Postcards.; Research notes.; Scrapbooks.; Atlantic Coast (N.J.); New Jersey -- Atlantic Coast.; Kimball, Sumner I. (Sumner Increase), 1834-1923; United States. Life-Saving Service
- Correspondence, circa 1890-1911 (Offsite-box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  The most frequent correspondent in the files is S.I. (Sumner Increase) Kimball, Superintendent of the Life-Saving Service of the U.S. Treasury Department, along with other officials in the Service. Correspondence, including that from Kimball, can also be found in the letterboxes listed below.
- Letterbox #1. Sandy Hook. Sandy Hook Point to Shrewsbury Inlet. General, 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 2, Volume 1)
- Letterbox #2. Sandy Hook., 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 2, Volume 2)
- Letterbox #3. Old Shrewsbury Beach. Shrewsbury Inlet to Long Branch. [Galilee, Sea Bright.] General. Wrecks, 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 2, Volume 3)
- Letterbox #4. Long Branch Beach. General. Wrecks., 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 3, Volume 4)
- Letterbox #5. [Deal, Asbury Park, Wesley Lake, Ocean Grove, Fletcher Lake to Shark River], 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 3, Volume 5)
- Letterbox #6. [Spring Lake, Belmar, Wreck Pond to Squan Inlet/River], 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 3, Volume 6)
- Letterbox #7. Squam Beach [or Squan Beach] [Point Pleasant, Bay Head, Mantoloking, Lavallette, Chadwick], 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 4, Volume 7)
- Letterbox #8. Island Beach. [Seaside Park.] General. Wrecks., 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 4, Volume 8)
- Letterbox #9. Barnegat Shoal, Long Beach. Wrecks., 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 4, Volume 9)
- Letterbox #10. Long Beach. General. Tucker's Beach, 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 5, Volume 10)
- Letterbox #11. Little Egg Harbor Shoal. Little Beach. General., 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 5, Volume 11)
- Letterbox #12. Brigantine Shoal. Brigantine Beach. General, 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 5, Volume 12)
- Letterbox #13. Absecon Shoal. Absecon Beach. [Atlantic City.] General., 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 6, Volume 13)
- Letterbox #14. Great Egg Harbor. Peck's Beach. [Ocean City.] General, 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 6, Volume 14)
- Letterbox #15. Corsons Inlet to Seven Mile Beach. [Sea Isle City, Ludlam Beach, Townsends Inlet] General. Wrecks., 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 6, Volume 15)
- Letterbox #16. Hereford Inlet to Two Mile Beach. [Holly Beach, Wildwoods, Turtle Gut.] General. Wrecks, 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 7, Volume 16)
- Letterbox #17. Cold Spring Inlet. Cape May. General. Wrecks, 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 7, Volume 17)
- Letterbox #18. [U.S. Life Saving Service (1846-1869)], 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 7, Volume 18)
- Letterbox #19. [U.S. Life Saving Service (1870-1913)], 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 8, Volume 19)
- Letterbox #20. [U.S. Life Saving Service (1914-1915); Wrecks and Wreck-related], 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 8, Volume 20)
- Letterbox #21. [U.S. Life Saving Service; Wrecks and Wreck-related], 1800s-1910s (Offsite-box 8, Volume 21)
- Nitrate negatives (Box 9)
  This box holds the nitrate negatives removed from the various files. The contents are in cold storage and are restricted. Permission from the manuscripts curator and conservator is required for access.